James A. Baker III Papers, 1957-2011 (bulk 1972-1992): Finding Aid MC197
Public Policy Papers
James A. Baker III Papers
1957-2011
1972-1992
Public Policy Papers
Baker, James Addison, 1930-
MC197
340 boxes
4 items
James A. Baker III served in senior government positions under three United States Presidents and was a central figure in the administrations of Ronald Reagan and George Bush in the 1980s and early 1990s. Baker also led presidential campaigns for Presidents Gerald Ford, Reagan and Bush over the course of five consecutive presidential elections from 1976 to 1992. The papers document nearly every stage of Baker's career, including his work on presidential campaigns, his time as White House Chief of Staff for both Reagan and Bush, and his terms as Secretary of the Treasury under Reagan and Secretary of State under Bush.
Scope and Contents
The James A. Baker III Papers document nearly every aspect of Baker's long career in politics and public service, including his time as White House Chief of Staff and Secretary of the Treasury under President Ronald Reagan, his term as Secretary of State under George H.W. Bush, and his work leading the presidential campaigns of Presidents Ford, Reagan, and Bush. Little documentation of Baker's time as Chief of Staff to President Bush from August 1992 to January 1993 is present in the papers.
The collection includes a variety of correspondence, memos, handwritten notes, speech transcripts, video and audio tapes, and other material related to Baker's positions in government and on political campaigns. The collection also includes material documenting Baker's legal career and early political efforts, including a substantial amount of correspondence with future President George H.W. Bush, written between Baker and Bush in the 1960s and 1970s. Substantial documentation of the 1978 Texas Attorney General Campaign, the only time Baker ran for political office himself, also exists.
Please see individual series descriptions for detailed information about the scope of each series.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use, with the following exceptions:
Interview transcripts in Series 12: The Politics of Diplomacy are closed unless permission, specific to each transcript, is granted by Secretary Baker as well as the person who gave the interview. Please contact the library for additional details. Audio cassette tapes of the same interviews in Series 14: Audiovisual Materials are also restricted; audio interviews related to The Politics of Diplomacy are closed unless permission, specific to each interview, is granted by Secretary Baker as well as the person who gave the interview.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The audiovisual series includes videotapes on VHS and various other formats. Access to these materials follows the Mudd Manuscript Library policy for preservation and access to audiovisual materials.
Custodial History
The Baker Papers were housed at the Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, at Rice University until December 2002. Material donated in October 2004 was previously kept at the Baker Institute for Public Policy at Rice University and Baker Botts law firm in Houston.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by James A. Baker III in 2002. Additional accessions were donated in October 2004, February 2011 and August 2011.
Appraisal
Duplicates, material of little evidential or information value, and strictly personal documents have been returned to Secretary Baker. A large volume of newspaper clippings from major American newspapers have also been returned.
The February 2011 accession originally included four additional series, which were subsequently separated.
A series of board membership records spanned Baker's pre- and post-Washington career (additionally, some files from his work on the boards of regional organizations during the 1960's and '70s were interspersed throughout his personal financial records). Board participation during his post-Washington career includes work with St. Luke's hospital, Rice University, the Howard Hughes Medical Institute, the University of Bremen, Electronic Data Systems, Radiant Energy Corporation, and King Ranch. These records encompassed twenty linear feet, were non-unique, and of extremely limited research value.
A series called soft costs documented accounting within Baker Botts of how to expense Baker's political work using Baker Botts resources was also removed from the collection. The series of two boxes consisted of spreadsheets of phone logs and billing codes, and no material regarding the substance of Baker's political work.
A series of campaign contributions from Baker's 1978 Attorney General campaign included two boxes of index cards of campaign contributors' contact information.
Finally, the "Income Tax Records" series is the only surviving part of what was once a series of personal financial records, spanning the 1960s through the beginning of the Reagan administration, which included cancelled checks, financial statements from investments, receipts, tax returns, trust statements, documentation from family legal issues and statements from charitable organizations. Because these records included personally identifiable information and were of limited research value, the vast majority were separated from the collection, although Baker's tax returns were retained.
Accruals
Accruals may occur at a later date.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm of the collection will be available at the Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, at Rice University.
Related Materials
Collections of related material are available at the presidential libraries of Presidents Ford, Reagan, and George H.W. Bush. The Reagan library includes a collection of Baker's White House files (BAKER, JAMES A. III: Files, 1981-1985). The library also has a number of collections related to Baker's assistants, including James Cicconi, Richard Darman, Frank Hodsoll, and Margaret Tutwiler, which contain a large amount of material documenting his work.
The Baker Institute for Public Policy maintains a collection of memorabilia, political cartoons, and select documents, as well as a large number of photographs. Many photographs of Baker may also be found in Official White House photograph collections available through the Reagan and Bush Libraries.
Researchers may also wish to contact the National Archives and Records Administration, as well as the Office of the Historian at the Department of State.
Baker, James Addison, 1930-
Biographical / Historical
The Leadership Documentary Project was created by PS Productions, a five-person multi-media production company that included Executive Producer Andrew M. Ling, Producer and Director Townley Patton, and PS Communication's director Phil Schwenk. In addition to the existing PS Production team, Mark Higbie was hired as Associate Producer and Coordinator, David Paton as the writer, and Jose A. Salgado as a videographer.
The documentary was the company's first major production and had the approval of James A. Baker III, a close friend of Townley Paton's father, David Paton '52.
Bibliography
The following works were consulted during preparation of the biographical note: Baker, James A. III, The Politics of Diplomacy: Revolution, War and Peace, 1989-1992. New York: George G. Putnam & Sons, 1995. Newhouse, John, "Profiles: The Tactician," [James A. Baker III], The New Yorker, 7 May 1990, pp/ 50-82.
Diplomacy.; Finance, Public--United States.; German reunification question (1949-1990).; Nuclear disarmament.; Legislation--United States.; Persian Gulf War, 1991.; Political campaigns--United States--20th century.; Political candidates--United States.; Post-communism.; Presidents--Election.; Presidential candidates.; Presidents--United States--Election--1972.; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Presidents--United States--Election--1984.; Presidents--United States--Election--1988.; Presidents--United States--Election--1992.; Presidents--United States--Election--1996.; Presidents--United States--Election--2000.; Presidents--United States--Staff.; Presidents--United States--Transition periods.; Statesmen--United States--Biography.; Statesmen--United States--Correspondence.; Tax reform.; World politics--1945-1989.; World politics--1989-; Texas--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Foreign policy--1981-; United States--Foreign relations--1981-1993.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Middle East.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1989-1993.; Correspondence.; Interviews.; Memorandums.; Reports.; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings.; Speeches.; Videotapes.; Born digital.; United States. Department of State; United States. Department of the Treasury; United States. President (1974-1977: Ford); United States. President (1981-1989: Reagan); United States. President (1989-1993: Bush); United States. White House Office; United States. White House Office. Office of Legislative Affairs; Middle East Peace Conference (1991: Madrid, Spain); Princeton University; Baker, James Addison, 1930-; Bush, George W. (George Walker), 1946-; Bush, George, 1924-2018.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Darman, Richard Gordon, 1943-2008; Dole, Robert J., 1923-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Hodsoll, Francis Samuel Monaise; Meese, Edwin; Moore, Preston, 1931-; Nixon, Richard M. Richard Milhous 1913-1994; Reagan, Nancy, 1921-2016; Reagan, Ronald; Rove, Karl; Scowcroft, Brent; Tower, John G. (John Goodwin), 1925-1991
- Series 1: Personal and Legal Career, 1930-1980; 12 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  The Personal and Legal Career series documents Baker's personal and professional life prior to his involvement in Texas and national politics. The series consists of correspondence, including correspondence with family and friends, diaries and date books, financial documents, legal documents, memos, and correspondence related to Baker's work at Andrews, Kurth, Campbell and Jones law firm, and personal documents such as a birth certificate and scholastic records.
  Arrangement
  The series is divided into 5 subseries.
  - Subseries 1A. Correspondence, 1957 May-1975; 3 boxes
    The Correspondence subseries consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence dating from 1957 through 1976. A substantial amount of material is personal in nature, including letters to and from family and friends, while a small amount of material is related to Baker's legal and political activities.
    The subseries is arranged chronologically. Materials within folders are in reverse chronological order.
    - 1957 May-1960 May, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1960 May-1961 April, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1961 May-1962 June, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1962 July-1964 December, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1965, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1966, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1968, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1969, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1970, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1971, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1972, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1973, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1974, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1975, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 1B. Diaries and Date Books, 1957-1979; 2 boxes
    The Diaries and Date Books subseries consists of Baker's diaries and date books from 1957 through 1979 (with the exception of 1976). The diaries list appointments, personal obligations, and work-related matters such as court cases. Two date books exist for both 1977 and 1978; information overlaps somewhat but is not duplicated.
    The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - 1957-1971, 1 box (Box 4)
    - 1972-1979, 1 box (Box 5)
  - Subseries 1C. Financial Records, 1969-1980; 1 box
    The Financial subseries consists of a small group of documents relating to some of Baker's financial matters in the 1960s and 1970s. Included are materials from Baker's involvement with Texas Commerce Bank.
    The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Ranch Properties, 1974-1980; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Texas Commerce Bank, 1969-1975; 1 box
      - Publicity and Congratulatory Letters, 1969-1975; 1 box
        - Advisory Director, 1969; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Director, 1975; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Sheshunoff and Company (Investment Banking), 1973; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Texas Constitutional Convention, 1974; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Trust Audit Committee, 1974-1975; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1969-1975; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 1D. Legal Career, 1957-1977; 5 boxes
    The Legal subseries consists of memoranda and reader files containing legal correspondence associated with court cases with which Baker was involved from 1957 through 1977. Also included are subject files that include documents related to Andrews, Kurth, Campbell and Jones, material concerning Baker's affiliation with state and local bar associations, and various legal documents.
    The subseries is arranged alphabetically
    - Memoranda, 1957-1973; 3 boxes
      - Miscellaneous Memos, 1957-1973; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
      - Miscellaneous Memos, 1957-1973 (continued), 7 folders (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
      - Miscellaneous Memos, 1957-1973 (continued) (1 Folder), 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Index to Miscellaneous Memos, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Interoffice and Personal, 1965-1969; 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Reader Files, 1973-1974; 1 box
      - General, 1973-1974; 3 folders (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
      - Harry R. Jones, 1974; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Subject Files, 1963-1977; 3 boxes
      - Andrews, Kurth, Campbell and Jones, 1964-1977; 2 boxes
        - Announcement of Baker's Return to Firm and Congratulations, 1977; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 9)
        - Partnership Agreements, 1964-1974; 2 folders (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
        - Partnership Agreement Drafts, 1969-1973; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - Telephone Record, 1974; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Time Summaries, 1973-1975; 3 folders (Box 9, Folder 5-7)
      - Application for Admission to United States Supreme Court, 1975-1977; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Bar Associations, 1963-1974; 1 box
        - Houston, 1963-1974; 1 box
          - Speech, 1969; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 9)
          - Miscellaneous, 1963-1974; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 10)
        - Texas, 1966-1972; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 11)
        - Miscellaneous, 1964-1969; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - United States versus Minton (Appointment to Indigent Federal Criminal Case), 1964; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous Legal Documents, 1972-1973; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 1E. Personal Subject Files, 1930-1979; 3 boxes
    The Personal Subject Files subseries consists of documents related to Baker's charitable work, Princeton alumni activities, and other non-professional matters. Included are personal documents such as Baker's birth certificate and Baker's military and scholastic records, as well as documents and notes relating to Baker's travels to China (to visit George Bush), Africa, and the western United States.
    - African Safari, 1974; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence from George Bush
    - Baker, James A. IV, 1971; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Biographical Sketch,1975-1977, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Birth Certificate, 1930; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Cabaniss, John, 1979; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Calhoun, Emma Lee, 1969; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - China Trip, 1975-1979; 1 box
      - Briefing Packet on the People's Republic of China for Ambassador and Mrs. George Bush and Friends, 1975-1977; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
    - Cosby, Fox, 1968; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Cosby, Maybelle, 1976; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Hill School, 1964-1969; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Houston-Harris County Fair Association, 1979; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Friends of the Texas Medical Center Library, 1975; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Lummis, William R, 1966-1971; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - McHenry, Albert Jerome, 1966; 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Military and Scholastic Records, 1954-1969; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Princeton University, 1963-1971; 1 box
      - General, 1963-1967; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Schools Committee, 1963-1971; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Requests for Papers, 1976-1978; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Ripley Foundation Board of Trustees, 1974-1975; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Rowley, Craig M, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Texas Children's Hospital, 1971-1977; 1 box
      - Board of Trustees, 1971; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Contractual Relations Committee, 1977; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Investment Advisory Committee, 1974-1975; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - University of Texas Health Sciences Center, 1978; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - White Water Float Expedition, 1977; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Widowed, Incorporated, 1971-1973; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Wills, 1954-1960; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Wilson, Viola Mazac, 1965; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Winston, Susan Garrett, 1973; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Woods, Bessie C, 1968; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1957-1974; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Early Political Career, 1964-1980; 4 boxes
  The Early Political Career series documents Baker's first forays into politics in the 1960s and 1970s. Most of the material is related to Republican organizations or political campaigns in Texas.
  The most significant materials in the series are the files related to George H.W. Bush, which include material related to Bush's Congressional and Senate campaigns, as well as files of correspondence and notes sent between Bush and Baker from the late 1960s to the mid-1970s, including letters sent between the two while Bush was serving as Ambassador to China.
  The Baker-Bush correspondence addresses a wide variety of subjects, both political and personal, and ranges from letters concerning Bush's early Congressional campaigns to light-hearted notes and attempts to schedule tennis matches. The general correspondence folder consists primarily of professional and political correspondence, while the personal notes, letters, and miscellaneous folder tends to contain material that is more personal in nature, although professional and personal material does overlap somewhat in both folders. Highlights of the correspondence include a note sent from Bush to Baker on the day after Bush was passed over for the Vice Presidency in the Ford Administration, and a two-page, single-spaced letter, apparently hand-typed by Bush, sent soon after Bush's arrival in China. In addition to correspondence, the Bush files also include Baker's "political file" from 1969, when Baker, encouraged by Bush and others, was considering running for the Congressional seat vacated when Bush decided to run for Senate. The material, including additional correspondence from Bush, documents Baker's decision not to run for the seat and also includes some material related Bush's Senate campaign and other political topics.
  The remainder of the early political career series documents Baker's involvement in various campaigns (i.e. Archer for Congress) and work with various Republican organizations such as the Republican State and Harris County Finance Committees and the Republican Congressional Boosters Club. There is also a concentration of material related to Senator John Tower (R-Texas).
  The series is divided into four major groupings. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Each remaining grouping is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Bush Files, 1964-1980; 1 box
    The correspondence addresses a wide variety of subjects, both political and personal, and ranges from letters concerning Bush's early Congressional campaigns to light-hearted notes and attempts to schedule tennis matches. The general correspondence folder consists primarily of professional and political correspondence, while the personal notes, letters, and miscellaneous folder tends to contain material that is more personal in nature, although professional and personal material does overlap somewhat in both folders. Highlights of the correspondence include a note sent from Bush to Baker on the day after Bush was passed over for the Vice Presidency in the Ford Administration, and a two-page, single-spaced letter, apparently hand-typed by Bush, sent soon after Bush's arrival in China. In addition to correspondence, the Bush files also include Baker's "political file" from 1969, when Baker, encouraged by Bush and others, was considering running for the Congressional seat vacated when Bush decided to run for Senate. The material, including additional correspondence from Bush, documents Baker's decision not to run for the seat and also includes some material related Bush's Senate campaign and other political topics.
    - Appreciation Dinner, 1974; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Baker Politics File, 1969; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Campaign Contributions, 1970; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1975; 1 box
      - General, 1966-1972; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Personal Notes, Letters, and Miscellaneous, 1969-1975; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 13)
        includes photographs
    - Finance Committee (Bush for Congress), 1964-1966; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Residency and Voter Registration, 1972-1980; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974-1975; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 16)
      primarily clippings related to CIA directorship
  - Correspondence, 1973-1975; 1 box
    - 1973, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1974, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1975, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Republican Finance Committees, 1968-1976; 2 boxes
    - Republican National Finance Committee, 1972-1973; 1 box
      - General, 1973; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 4)
        includes George Bush correspondence
      - Armstrong, Anne, 1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - State Finance Committee, 1968-1976; 2 boxes
      - Budget, 1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Bush Regional Campaign Coordinators, 1970-1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Campaign Financing laws (proposed changes), 1971-1973; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Direct Mailings and Ivory Club, 1968-1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Financial Statements and Reports, 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Harris County, 1969-1976; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Key Republican Solicitations, 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - National Committee, 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Organization, 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Salute to the President Dinner, 1971; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - State Convention (Dallas), 1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - State Convention (Galveston), 1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - State Republican Executive Committee Meetings (S.R.E.C.), 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Harris County Finance Committee, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Subject Files, 1971-1978; 1 box
    - Archer for Congress, 1974; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 1)